Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Arnold Grisman Papers, 1934-1997 and undated, bulk 1969-1987
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Arnold Grisman papers 1934-1997 and undated, bulk 1969-1987
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company
4.2 linear feet Extent: 3150 Items
The J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT), founded in 1864, is one of the oldest and largest enduring advertising agencies in the United States. Arnold Grisman joined JWT as a copywriter in 1955. Grisman held a number of positions during his career with JWT, and rose to become Creative Director of the New York Office and an Executive Vice President. A prolific writer, Grisman produced numerous short stories, three published novels, and speeches for other JWT executives. The Arnold Grisman Papers span the years 1934-1997, with the bulk of materials spanning 1969-1987, and includes correspondence, speeches, presentations, memoranda, manuscripts, photographs, videocassettes and publications that document Grisman's work on a number of projects. Materials in collection represent work on a proposed collection of the writings of early JWT executive James Webb Young; research on the JWT London Office; Grisman's consultant work for the 1969 NASA Space Task Force Report; interviews with Dick Lord, Frank Stanton, John Goodyear, Bob Dilenscheider, Ron Kovas, Joe O'Donnell, and Jack Peters, for JWT's 1986 Annual Report; internal executive reports; publications by and about JWT; proceedings from an experimental TV commercial workshop; a 1973 presentation to the Ford Motor Company; a typescript of We aim to bring results by John Philip Jones (later edited and published as Does It Pay To Advertise? by Lexington Books, Lexington, Mass., 1989); and notes and early drafts of a writing project entitled Rush Hour. Other JWT staff represented in the collection include George Black, George Butler, Sidney Bernstein, Steve Darland, Colin Dawkins, Ken Hinks, Marion Howington, Don Johnston, Stephen King, Howard Kohl, Denis Lanigan, Burt Manning, Sam Meek, Donald Marschner, and Nancy Stephenson.
RL.00705
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
However, original audiovisual materials are closed to researchers; Use Copies are available in the collection.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The J. Walter Thompson Company. Arnold Grisman Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a transfer in 1987, with additions in 2001.
Biographical Note
1920 Sept. 5 Born, Arnold Ellis Grisman
1941 B.A. in English, Harvard University
1942 M.A. in English, Columbia University
1947 Left Columbia University without completing Ph.D in English
1955 Joined JWT as copywriter; worked primarily for Ford Thunderbird account
1960 Feb. 15 Leave of Absence to work on Ford Canadian Car X account
1960 May 16 Worked on Shell Oil Co. account
1963 Elected vice president of JWT
1966 Named Creative Supervisor
1971 Appointed Creative Director, New York and elected Executive Vice President of JWT
1985 Celebrated 30th anniversary of employment with JWT
2008 Mar. 12 Died, Albany, N.Y.
In addition, Grisman wrote extensively and published three novels: Early to Rise (1958); Bongo (1961); and The Winning Streak (1985).
Collection Overview
The Arnold Grisman Papers span the years 1934-1997, with the bulk of materials spanning 1969-1987, and includes correspondence, speeches, presentations, memoranda, manuscripts, photographs, videocassettes and publications that document Grisman's work on a number of projects. Materials in collection represent work on a proposed collection of the writings of early JWT executive James Webb Young; research on the JWT London Office; Grisman's consultant work for the 1969 NASA Space Task Force Report; interviews with Dick Lord, Frank Stanton, John Goodyear, Bob Dilenscheider, Ron Kovas, Joe O'Donnell, and Jack Peters, for JWT's 1986 Annual Report; internal executive reports; publications by and about JWT; proceedings from an experimental TV commercial workshop; a 1973 presentation to the Ford Motor Company; a typescript of We aim to bring results by John Philip Jones (later edited and published as Does It Pay To Advertise? by Lexington Books, Lexington, Mass., 1989); and notes and early drafts of a writing project entitled Rush Hour. Other JWT staff represented in the collection include George Black, George Butler, Sidney Bernstein, Steve Darland, Colin Dawkins, Ken Hinks, Marion Howington, Don Johnston, Stephen King, Howard Kohl, Denis Lanigan, Burt Manning, Sam Meek, Donald Marschner, and Nancy Stephenson.
The Collection is organized into three series: Printed Materials, Photographs, and Audiovisual Materials. The Printed Materials Series consists primarily of speeches, presentations and memoranda, as well as research materials for a proposed collection of the writings of early JWT executive James Webb Young. The Photographs Series includes transparencies, prints, and negatives of JWT's U.S. and European staff. The Audiovisual Materials Series consists of 5 videotapes that accompanied Mr. Grisman's major presentations.
Subject Headings
Grisman, Arnold; Bernstein, Sidney Ralph, 1907-; Black, George; Dawkins, Colin; Hinks, Kennett Webb, 1897-1982; Johnston, Don, 1927-; Jones, John Philip; Jones, John Philip. Does it pay to advertise?: cases illustrating successful brand advertising; Kohl, Howard; Lanigan, Denis, 1926-; Manning, Burt; Meek, Samuel W. (Samuel Williams), b. 1895; Stanton, Frank, 1908-2006; Young, James Webb, 1886-; Ford Motor Company; J. Walter Thompson Company; J. Walter Thompson. London office; United States. National Aeronautics and Space Administration -- History; Advertising executives -- United States; Advertising agencies -- Great Britain -- History; Advertising agencies -- United States -- History; Business presentations; Television advertising; Speeches; Memoranda; Videocassettes; Photographs; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Related Material
For further research, other materials relating to this collection may be found in the following collections within The J. Walter Thompson Company Archives: the Colin Dawkins Papers, the Sidney Ralph Bernstein Company History Files, the Don Johnston Papers, the Frankfurt Office. Denis Lanigan Papers, the Frankfurt Office. George Black Papers and the World War II Advertising Collection.
Contents of Collection
- Printed Materials Series, 1934-1997 and undated, (7 Boxes)
  Contains speeches, interviews, presentations, proceedings, clippings, and correspondence that document the work of key JWT staff, including that of Grisman. Also contains a proposed collection of writings by James Webb Young dating from the 1930s through 1960s. Arranged alphabetically.
  - Grisman Personal Writings
    - Desensitization of America, 1975-1976, (3 folders) (Box 1)
    - Rush Hour draft and supporting materials, 1997 and undated (Box 1)
    - What's New Pussycat? 1965; and The Restless Scene, 1966 (Box 1)
    - X-Rated Society, circa 1975 (Box 1)
  - JWT Staff
    - Black, George, JWT Frankfurt Report, 1983 (Box 1)
    - Butler, George, George Butler Remembers..., 1985 and A History of Berkeley Square, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Dawkins, Colin
      - Biographical, 1986-1987 (Box 1)
      - JWT history project, 1978-1980 (Box 1)
      - Writings, 1986 and undated (Box 1)
    - Grisman, Arnold
      - Before and After, 1972 (Box 1)
      - How to Keep Your Television Budget from Disappearing, drafts, 1985 (Box 1)
      - Interviews for Annual Report, featuring Bob Dilenschneider and Ron Kovas; Dick Lord; Frank Stanton; Joe O'Donnell and Jack Peters; and John Goodyear, 1986, (5 folders) (Box 1)
      - Materials for NASA Space Task Force Assignment, 1969, (2 folders) (Box 2)
      - Memoranda and other materials, 1981-1988 (Box 2)
      - Wrestling with the Corporate Conscience, 1983, with clipping about Grisman from issue of Madison Avenue, 1973 (Box 2)
    - Hinks, Ken, original script for talk on JWT history, 1982 (Box 2)
    - Howington, Marion, J. Walter Thompson: A Legend in his own Time, 1988 (Box 2)
    - Johnston, Don
      - American Association of Advertising Agencies: A Report from the Chairman to the AAA Annual Meeting 1982 (Box 2)
      - American Consumer 1970-1990: Great Expectations 1977 (Adapted from a speech by Johnston.) (Box 2)
      - JWT Recruit Program (Original), 1981 (Box 2)
      - Look at the Company You Have Joined, 1984 (Box 2)
      - Marketing in the Global Village, 1985 (Box 2)
      - Quick Tour Through The Past, Present, and Future of Advertising, 1981 (Box 2)
      - Re-examination of the Process of Branding (Original), 1981 (Box 2)
      - Trends in American Advertising (Original), 1981 (Box 2)
      - Voice and Conscience of an Industry, 1983 (Box 2)
    - Jones, John Philip, We Aim To Bring Results, manuscript, circa 1989, (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - King, Stephen, Market Modeling, circa 1978 (Box 2)
    - Kohl, Howard Through the Years with Howard Kohl, 1985 (Box 2)
    - Lanigan, Denis
      - Advertising in Crisis Situations (A Survival Manual for Bad Times), 1983-1984 (Box 2)
      - Advertising Wars, 1985 (Box 3)
      - Cola Wars, 1985-1986 (Box 3)
      - It's a Long Way Down to the Creative Department, or Information and its Discontents, 1986 (Box 3)
      - What is Multinationality? Can it be Cured? 1983-1984 (Box 3)
      - Where it Comes From, Where it is Today, Where it Appears to be Going, 1984 (Box 3)
    - Manning, Burt
      - Big Idea, 1988 (Box 3)
      - Birth of a Giant, essay by Donald Merschner with letter from Merschner to Manning, 1962, and 1988 (Box 3)
      - In Our Hands, circa 1987; The Soul of a Company, 1988; How Bad Is It? circa 1988 (Box 3)
      - Responses to Questions by Media Key, circa 1988; In Our Hands, 1987; presentation and notes, 1987 (Box 3)
      - Untitled presentation and notes, 1987 (Box 3)
    - Stephenson, Nancy, Why Women? 1962 (Box 3)
      Unilever conference paper.
    - Wade, James, The Seventies: A Marketing View, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Young, James Webb
      - Biographical material, circa 1975-1986, (2 folders) (Box 3)
      - Interviews, 1963-1986 (Box 3)
        [Interviewers: Colin Dawkins, Sidney Bernstein. Includes photocopy of Young's 1986 stockholder's affidavit]
      - Lectures 1934 (Box 3)
      - Posthumous publishing efforts by Grisman, et. al., 1985-1988, (2 folders) (Box 4)
      - What Jim Young Said and What He Didn't Say, speech given by Jeremy Bullmore, European Managers Meeting, 1978 (Box 4)
  - JWT London office
    - Close-Up London (A and B), 1985 (Box 4)
    - Explanatory letter from Hilda to Colin Dawkins about Sam Meek, 1986 (Box 4)
    - For OCT/NOV JWT News: Before Berkeley Square, JWT London, undated (Box 4)
    - JWT London Office History, 1966-1983 (Box 4)
    - JWT London Post WWII, 1965-1983 (Box 4)
    - JWT London research materials, 1958-1977 and undated (Box 4)
    - The New Sam Meek Piece, 1986 and undated (Box 4)
  - Presentations/Proceedings
    - Around the World in 80 Years, circa 1984 and J. Walter Thompson Company, 1987 (Box 4)
    - European Managers' meeting, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Ford presentation, 1973, (1-3 of 4 folders) (Box 4)
    - Ford presentation (continued), 1973, (4 of 4 folders) (Box 5)
    - How Long Should an Advertisement Be? 1956-1962 and undated (Box 5)
    - The Image of an Imaging Company, Kodak presentation, 1983 (Box 5)
    - Institutional Investors, JWT Presentation, 1994 Aug. 24 (Box 5)
    - Managers' meeting (Don Johnston and Denis Lanigan), 1984 (Box 5)
    - The Process of Self-Regulation in Advertising: A Presentation by the National Advertising Review Council to the U.S. Senate Commerce Committee, 1981 (Box 5)
    - Project Alpha Experimental TV Workshop, 1971 (Box 5)
    - Speeches, 1970-1979, (5 folders) (Box 5)
    - The T-Plan File, 1973 (Box 5)
    - Trouble at the Credibility Gap, 1974 (Box 5)
    - Worldwide Slide Presentation/Profile Book, 1985 (Box 5)
  - Publications by and about JWT
    - Ad Week and Advertising Age, 1987 (Box 6)
      [Features cover stories on JWT]
    - Recent Events, (clipping collection), 1982 (Box 6)
    - Recent Events Book VI, News Coverage, JWT Syndication Situation, (clipping collection), 1982 (Box 6)
    - Recent Events VII, Second Quarter, Gray Lawsuit, (clipping collection), 1982 (Box 6)
- Photographs Series, circa 1980-1982 and undated, (1 Box)
  Includes color transparencies, black-and-white and color prints of JWT American and European staff.
  - J. Walter Thompson, undated (Box 6)
  - JWT European offices and staff, circa 1980 (Box 6)
  - JWT European offices and staff, circa 1980 (Box 6)
  - JWT New York, undated (Box 6)
  - Latin American Manager's Meeting, 1982 (Box 6)
- Audiovisual Materials Series, 1976 and undated, 2 Boxes
  Consists of videotapes that accompanied Grisman's major presentations, Originals are closed to researchers; use copies are available in the collection.
  - Originals (CLOSED)
    - OR 1. Kraft 75th Anniversary, part one. Format: Umatic. Undated. See use copy, UC1. (Box 7)
    - OR 2. Kraft 75th Anniversary, part two. Format: Umatic. Undated. See use copy, UC2. (Box 7)
    - OR 3. Roots of Human Communication. Format: Umatic. Undated. See use copy, UC3. (Box 7)
    - OR 4. Desensitization of America, 1976. Format: Umatic. 1976. See use copy, UC4. (Box 7)
    - OR 5. Desensitization of America. Format: Umatic. Undated. See use copy, UC5. (Box 7)
  - Production Masters (Not for research use)
    - MC1-MC5. Masters for OR1-OR5. Format: Betacam SP. Created: 2008. (Box 8)
  - Use Copies
    - UC1-UC5. Use copies for OR1-OR5. Format: DVD. Created: 2008. (Box 6)